Overview Guide to the New-York Historical Society Records 1804-2018 NYHS-RG Archives
New-York Historical Society
1858 A Publication Fund is established to finance the production of a new series of the Collections of The New-York Historical Society.
1859 James Lenox Collection of Assyrian relief carvings donated.
1859 N-YHS publishes A Catalogue of the Printed Books in the Library, the last of its kind. It includes about 25,000 volumes. Future catalogs of the books will consist of cards or, in the late 20th century, public databases.
1860 N-YHS purchases the Abbott collection of about 1,100 Egyptian artifacts. It goes on display the following year.
1860 N-YHS forms a special committee to pursue the possibility of establishing a Museum of Antiquities, Science, and Art in Central Park. The possibility lingers into the late 1860s before fading completely in the 1870s.
1862 N-YHS's Committee on Fine Arts makes an appeal in its Annual Report for donations of photographs, which it has been gradually collecting since at least 1857.
1863 N-YHS purchases John J. Audubon's watercolors for Birds of America from his widow, Lucy.
1867 Thomas Jefferson Bryan donates his collection of European art to N-YHS. Additional objects are bequeathed by Bryan at his death in 1870.
1868 The first volume of the Publication Fund series of the Collections is issued.
1869 The American Museum of Natural History is founded. Its opening exhibits appear in 1871 in the Central Park Arsenal, the home N-YHS had pursued in the 1860s.
1870 The Metropolitan Museum of Art opens at a midtown location. It moves to Central Park in 1880.
1870 NYHS purchases drawings of North American Indians by George Catlin.
1871 At its March meeting, N-YHS hears its first paper written by a woman, Martha Lamb, read by Librarian George Moore. Lamb herself would read a paper to N-YHS in 1878, likely the first reading by a woman to the Society.
1891 N-YHS purchases ten lots on Central Park West for a new building, but has no funds for construction.
1880 N-YHS forms a Building Committee to gather subscriptions for a new building. Little money is committed until later in the decade.
1893 By this date, the library holds about 100,000 volumes.
1898 The trustees of the New York Public Library propose that N-YHS consolidate with the library, but the N-YHS Executive Committee declines.
1902 Construction started on the central portion of the new Central Park West building, designed by York & Sawyer. Funds are still insufficient and will only gradually be accumulated.
1904 N-YHS celebrates its centennial anniversary at Delmonico's restaurant. It votes to exclude the women members from the banquet and relegates them to the balcony with nonmembers for the post-dinner orations.
1908 N-YHS moves its collections into the new building. The public is now welcome without needing a member introduction.
1908 John Watts DePeyster bequeaths $25,000, in part to the endowment of the Publication Fund, which is then renamed the John Watts DePeyster Fund in conformance with the terms of the bequest.
1909 N-YHS installs a Robert Fulton loan exhibition, in official connection with the city-wide Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
1917 A member, Mrs. John King (Mae) Van Rensselaer, criticizes N-YHS management at a Society meeting. These criticisms are reported by the press and reforms are considered in N-YHS.
1917 A series of new programs are implemented: cataloguing and conservation work was started on the Egyptian collection, a series of free illustrated lectures for schoolchildren on Saturday afternoons was conducted, a new publication, the Quarterly Bulletin, was initiated, and the Audubon watercolors were exhibited. Five new employees were added to the library and a bookkeeper was hired.
1917 A by-law amendment is adopted that vests almost complete management authority for N-YHS with the Executive Committee, ending the need for regular business meetings of the membership.
1918 The Field Exploration Committee is formed to conduct digs for historic artifacts. The Committee exists until circa 1937.
1921 Longtime N-YHS library assistant Alexander J. Wall replaces Robert Kelby as Librarian.
1925 The collections of the Naval History Society are donated to N-YHS.
1925 N-YHS begins to expand its property ownership in anticipation of future building expansion. It purchases the former Oscar Strauss townhouse at 5 West 76th street. Other purchases on West 76th and 77th streets are made in the 1920s and 1930s. The townhouses are used as annexes for storage and exhibitions.
1925 A gold medal award for achievement in history is inaugurated. Isaac Newton Phelps Stokes is the first recipient.
1926 The Bella Landauer Collection of Business and Professional History is donated.
1929 An in-house bindery is established. It exists until 1960.
1935 A bequest of about $4.6 million from the Thompson estate is received from 1935-1942. It is used to complete the Central Park West building, expand the staff substantially (eventually to about 75 people), and build the endowment.
1937 Construction starts on the expansion of the Central Park West building. It is completed and the building re-opened in 1939. Designed by Walker & Gillette, major changes include the addition of north and south wings and a fifteen tier book stack.
1937 The Abbott Egyptian collection and other antiquities are loaned to the Brooklyn Museum. Most of these are sold to the museum in the 1940s.
1937 N-YHS reorganizes. The Executive Committee is replaced by an independent Board of Trustees and the former Librarian position takes the title of Director, recognizing the position's traditional responsibility for the entire organization. The organization expands into specialized departments staffed by discipline-specific professionals.
1937 N-YHS purchases the Elie Nadelman Folk Art collection.
1942 Precautions are taken against the possibility of air raid damage, including storage of some of the collection outside the city.
1944 Alexander Wall dies, replaced by R.W.G. Vail, State Librarian of New York.
1954 N-YHS celebrates it 150th anniversary. Among the commemorations is the publication of Director Vail's history of N-YHS, Knickerbocker Birthday.
1959 N-YHS adopts a formal acquisitions policy for the first time. It will be updated in 1971 and from time to time afterward.
1966 A major renovation adds air-conditioning, better ventilation, and other protective climate control measures.
1970s An economic downturn and the cost of N-YHS programs and operations combine to create financial stress that will not begin to ease until the mid-1990s.
1971 Visitors to N-YHS numbers 371,000 for the year.
1971 N-YHS sold at auction about 200 paintings from the Bryan collection. Additional out of scope works were sold in the 1980s and mid-1990s.
1972 Arthur J. Breton produces the first comprehensive catalogue of N-YHS's manuscript collections since the early nineteenth century.
1979 Faced with ongoing financial stress in the organization, N-YHS staff unionize. The library is closed for several months due to a strike during contract negotiations.
1980 N-YHS begins the years-long process of transferring information from its 300,000 item library card catalog to an on-line publicly accessible catalog.
1987 A stock market crash compounds N-YHS's severe financial difficulties.
1993 Continuing financial difficulty force the closing of the museum in January and library in February. State and city funding, the first in over a century, allows the library to re-open. Slowly, recovery occurs in the following years.
2000 The Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, used to house and exhibit thousands of museum objects, is opened.
2001 The endowment mounts to $33 million (from $7.6 million in 1988).
2004 N-YHS celebrates its bicentennial. Among the commemorations is a special issue of Antiques magazine and a new history of N-YHS by former Librarian Larry E. Sullivan.
2005 A major exhibition, Slavery in New York, is installed.
Bibliography
The N-YHS archives have been used over the years for histories, catalogues, articles, blogs, and other published matter written by N-YHS staff or on behalf of N-YHS and published by N-YHS. Such publications are not included in this list. This list includes only those publications prepared by authors from outside the organization that cited sources in the N-YHS archive. The list was started in 2015 and includes only known material so it is not necessarily complete.
Pamela Spence Richards, Scholars and Gentlemen: The Library of the New-York Historical Society, 1804-1982 (Hamden, Conn: Archon Books, 1984).
Tom Glynn, Reading Publics: New York City's Public Libraries, 1754-1911 (New York: Empire State Editions, 2015).
Museums -- New York (State) -- New York.; Correspondence.; Posters.; Libraries -- Gifts, legacies.; Legal documents.; Wills.; Bequests; Exhibition catalogs; Videocassettes.; Audiocassettes; Museum docents -- New York (State) -- New York.; Contracts.; United States Constitution Bicentennial, 1987-1991; Sales catalogs; Certificates.; Museum stores -- New York (State) -- New York.; Resource programs (Education) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Museum outreach programs; Outreach programs in history; Minute books.; Invoices.; Scrapbooks.; Architectural records.; Accounts.; Annual reports.; Membership lists.; Receipts (financial records); New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Acquisitions (Libraries) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Associations, institutions, etc. -- Membership -- New York (State) -- New York.; Genealogists -- Correspondence.; Librarians -- Correspondence.; Speeches (documents); Manuscripts (documents); Lectures.; Lists (document genres); Financial records.; Checks (bank checks); Dues -- New York (State) -- New York.; Registers (lists); Receipts (financial records); Bookkeeping registers; Exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Buildings -- Design and construction.; Publicity.; Letterpress copybooks.; negatives (photographs); Specifications.; Subscription lists; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Museum exhibits -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Architectural firms -- New York (State) -- New York.; Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909 -- Exhibitions; Historians; Clippings (information artifacts); Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Photographs.; Libraries -- New York (State) -- New York.; Press releases.; Printed ephemera -- New York (State) -- New York.; Tickets.; Museum registration methods -- New York (State) -- New York.; Promotional materials.; Central Park West (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Ephemera.; Calendars.; Brochures.; Accessions registers.; United States -- History -- Study and teaching.; School contests -- New York (State) -- New York.; Admission tickets.; Eulogies (documents).; Invitations.; Programs (documents).; Historians -- Correspondence.; Competition entries; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Essays.; Editing; Congresses and conventions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Art historians -- Correspondence; Proofs (printed matter); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; New-York Historical Society -- Anniversaries, etc.; New-York Historical Society -- Press coverage; Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission -- Correspondence; Koch, G. Adolf (Gustav Adolf), 1900-; Wood, James Playsted, 1905-1983; Columbia University. Department of History; New-York Historical Society -- Buildings; New-York Historical Society -- Membership; New-York Historical Society -- Publishing; New-York Historical Society. Publication Fund; New-York Historical Society. John Watts De Peyster Publication Fund; New-York Historical Society -- Centennial celebrations, etc.; New-York Historical Society -- Public relations; New-York Historical Society. Library -- Sources; New-York Historical Society -- Management; New-York Historical Society. Executive Committee; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; Wallace, David H. -- Correspondence; Sawitzky, William, 1879 or 1880-1947 -- Correspondence; Sawitzky, Susan Clay, 1897-1981 -- Correspondence; Groce, George Cuthbert, 1899-1962 -- Correspondence; Gottesman, Rita Susswein, 1906-1963 -- Correspondence; Dickson, Harold E., 1900- -- Correspondence; Cowdrey, Mary Bartlett, 1910-1974 -- Correspondence; Bolton, Theodore, 1889-1973 -- Correspondence; Baker, Charles E. (Charles Edwin), 1902- -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society. Editorial Department; York & Sawyer; Walker & Gillette; Turner Construction Company; Andrew J. Robinson Company; Stevens, John Austin, 1827-1910 -- Correspondence; Moore, George Henry, 1823-1892 -- Correspondence
- NYHS-RG 1. Management committee records (1804-1938)
  Scope and Contents Note
  The New-York Historical Society management committee records group includes records associated with the organization's governance structure of 1804-1937. The record group includes minute books from the meetings of the Society's members (1804-1937) and from the meetings of the Executive Committee (1842-1937), as well as from other committees and the first year (1938) of the newly-constituted Board of Trustees. The record group also includes files of so-called official papers, which include ad hoc committee reports, draft annual reports, correspondence, financial information, membership nominations, and other material directly related to the proceedings of the Society and Executive Committee meetings.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Management Committee Records.
- NYHS-RG 2. General correspondence (1805-2018, bulk 1805-1982)
  The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group contains chronologically arranged communications directed to and from the institution and its officers. The bulk of correspondence through the early twentieth century is incoming only, though some notes, responses, and letterpress copybooks (1876-1911) of outgoing correspondence appear. Carbon copies of outgoing correspondence commonly appear after the early twentieth century. The files are predominated by requests for reference assistance; research reports; inquiries pertaining to membership and library operations; proposals of materials for donation, sale, or transfer; arrangements for lectures, events, and publications; acceptances of election to member or officer positions; financial transactions; requests for material exchanges; and invitations, circulars, and other printed matter generated by N-YHS and outside institutions. Correspondents include N-YHS officers, prominent historians, politicians, writers and lecturers, scientists, genealogists, artists, printers and booksellers, and colleagues from libraries, societies, government agencies, and other organizations.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence.
- NYHS-RG 3. Original buildings planning & construction records (1848-1946)
  The New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records include material concerning construction of the two buildings by N-YHS that served as its home from 1857-1908 (2nd Avenue and 11th Street) and from 1908 to the present (Central Park West, between West 76th and 77th streets). The record group includes both the construction of the Central Park West building's central portion in the first decade of the twentieth century and the major expansion of the building in the late 1930s. These records include documentation related to the planning and administration of the construction projects, contracts, financial matters, and over 1200 architectural and other plans, primarily in connection with the 1937-1938 expansion. The record group also includes correspondence and other substantive matter related to N-YHS's unsuccessful attempt in the 1860s and 1870s to establish in Central Park a Museum of Antiquities, Science, and Art.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Original Building Planning & Construction Records.
- NYHS-RG 4. Building renovations and maintenance records (1938-2017)
  The New-York Historical Society building renovations and maintenance records include files concerning the Central Park West physical plant from the late 1940s and forward. One major initiative that is especially well-documented in the record group is the extensive renovation work that began in planning about 1989 and concluded in 2000 with the opening of the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture. Various other large and small construction and maintenance projects are documented to some extent. The record group will continue to accrue new material over time.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Building Renovations and Maintenance Records.
- NYHS-RG 5. Pictorial archive (1804-2009, bulk 1900s-1970s)
  The N-YHS pictorial archive contains photographs, sketches, and drawings relating to the history of the New-York Historical Society: its buildings, exhibits, programs, staff, and officers. Most of the collection consists of photographs.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Pictorial Archive.
- NYHS-RG 6. Field Exploration Committee photographs (1891-1930s)
  The New-York Historical Society Field Exploration Committee photographs record group primarily includes images of materials resulting from the excavations for historical artifacts conducted by members of the Committee, mostly in the early twentieth century. These images are primarily from sites in upper Manhattan and the Bronx and include such materials as buttons from American and British uniforms and coins from the Revolutionary War and War of 1812. Also included are images of Native American materials discovered. These materials informed and illustrated the many articles written by William L. Calver and Reginald P. Bolton and published in N-YHS's Quarterly Bulletin during the Committee's existence from 1917-1938.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Field Exploration Committee Photographs.
- NYHS-RG 7. Press clippings (1843-2013)
  The New-York Historical Society press clippings record group includes material compiled regularly by N-YHS into scrapbooks and subject files from published sources from about 1870 to 1995, with some clippings as early as 1843. There are a relatively small number of post-1995 articles, principally print-outs of pages from Internet-based sources. Subjects include exhibitions, lectures, publications, and other programs; acquisitions of new collections or objects; building construction, management controversies, and other institutional matters; and leadership changes, obituaries, and other matters connected to individuals. The record group provides insight from over a century into the extent of press coverage of N-YHS and press perceptions of the organization and its programs, and a broad overview of events in N-YHS's history as presented in the press.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Press Clippings.
- NYHS-RG 8. Public relations material (circa 1939-2006)
  The New-York Historical Society public relations material record group contains press releases and press kits produced by N-YHS's Public Relations Department primarily between 1941 and 1993, with some subsequent material. The materials principally hold descriptive information about exhibitions, film series, and other programs presented by N-YHS. The releases also include publicity about organizational matters, such as new collection acquisitions, fundraising initiatives, and the like.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Public Relations Material.
- NYHS-RG 9. Membership records (1804-1983)
  The New-York Historical Society membership records includes material related to the basic administration of membership, that is, maintaining records of who was a member and whether their dues had been paid. The record group includes registers, or lists, of members, dues payment status, and certificates and other forms of membership-related ephemera.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Membership Records.
- NYHS-RG 10. John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund records (1857-1982)
  The New-York Historical Society's Publication Fund was formed in 1858 to provide the financial means of publishing annual volumes of N-YHS's Collections. Taking the name John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund in 1908, the Fund was used to produce 85 volumes from 1868 to 1975. These volumes were distributed to Fund shareholders and to other institutions in exchanges of publications. This record group primarily includes the registers, correspondence, and other records concerning shareholder administration, such as certificate purchases and transfers of ownership, and publication distribution. The record group also includes the offering circulars, subscription book, certificate books, some nineteenth century financial records, and other documents.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society John Watts DePeyster Publication Fund Records.
- NYHS-RG 11. Manuscripts of lectures and addresses (1809-1957, 2001, 2015-2016)
  This record group principally includes a manuscript form of about 150 addresses presented at N-YHS. The bulk of these are papers read or other prepared remarks made at N-YHS from the 1840s through the 1930s. Most typically, the manuscripts are from historians and other individuals of some renown, with few from figures of national prominence. Most of the addresses concern some aspect of early New York history, particular NYHS accomplishments, or broader reflections on the study and lessons of history and on America.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Manuscripts of Lectures and Addresses.
- NYHS-RG 12. Celebratory and memorial event records (1854-1954)
  The New-York Historical Society celebratory and memorial event record group includes correspondence, invitations, event programs, tickets, and other material associated with about twenty of the special events held by N-YHS from 1854-1954. These events included major N-YHS anniversaries, commemorations of Washington Irving (1860) and William Cullen Bryant (1878), the completion of the Central Park West building (1939), and others. The record group also includes documents related to the Robert Fulton exhibition installed at N-YHS in 1909 in conjunction with the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Celebratory and Memorial Event Records.
- NYHS-RG 13. Scholarship essay submissions (1925-1933)
  The record group includes twelve essays concerning New York City history submitted by Columbia University undergraduates in connection with the competition for a scholarship sponsored annually by New-York Historical Society from 1925-1933.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Scholarship Essay Submissions.
- NYHS-RG 14. Ephemera (1839-2019)
  The New-York Historical Society ephemera record group is comprised of print materials generated for distribution by the institution between 1839 and 2019 and documents N-YHS communication, programming, outreach, and promotion throughout its years of operation. Ephemera includes admission tickets; invitations; informational brochures; souvenir exhibition programs and checklists; event programs, handouts, calendars and schedules; library, museum, and membership announcements; bookplates and stationery; posters, postcards, flyers, and other promotional items.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Ephemera Record Group.
- NYHS-RG 15. Collection accession registers (1841-1962, 2002)